Right, so I keep saying long term I said this
multiple times in the earlier lectures also,
but what really is long term right.
.
So we will try to quantify that now right,
by introducing the notion of something called
return right, so this is a common notation
that I will use throughout where T indicates
the timestamp of the end of the episode T
means the end of the episode rate essentially
I have reached S+ right, so this could this
is the most natural way of thinking about
long term return correct, is the most natural
way of thinking about long-term return and
if there, if that T is actually finite right,
so this is actually is not a bad idea and
I will sum up all the word I'm going to get
in the feature and I will try to optimize
that, okay.
So again you can see that if I try to optimize
each one of these individually what will happen
I might get a very high RT+1 and RT+2 but
it might put me in such a bad ST+2 from then
on even if I behave optimally individually
for each of this these numbers might be small,
right. So what I really want to do is behave
in such a way that even if some of these numbers
are small right overall in the future the
somewhere I am going to get should be the
maximum, right.
So overall sum should be maximum, so that
is essentially the goal that I have here,
okay so this is fine it works fine that is
one circumstance where this would not work
when T is I mean there is no end right, so
I just keep doing this for forever if I keep
solving a problem forever then it becomes
a problem and not necessarily forever if I
am also doing something over very, very, very
long horizon if T is very large not necessarily
infinite but T is very large also I get into
some issues, okay because this will become
quantity with a large variance, okay. So one
other thing I should point out this is something
which people miss and get confused sometimes
while reading on their own so T here is a
random variable, right.
So every time I run the system it might stop
at a different time I think of playing chess
right, that is a finite endpoint chess will
end, but every time I play the game I do not
stop at the same number of moves, right in
something like tic-tac-toe right. Even though
there is an upper limit on the number of moves
you can make right, it is not necessary that
you will always end up playing if I moves
that you might end you might win in four moves
you might win in well yeah, if you win in
three moves well, okay.
My opponent is really bad but so it could
win in three moves you could win in four moves
or you could win in five moves, right or you
cannot win at all win so you could still end
up draw in the game so like that so T is a
random variable so when I put T here does
not mean it always runs for some T steps okay,
so every time I run it will be a different
value for T so remember that, right and consequently
Gt is also a random variable because all of
these are random variables I am talking about
some sort random variables, okay.
And a random number of those random variables
are being summed up okay, so Gt is also a
random variable that denotes the return okay,
great. So another notion of return that people
typically use is right, in fact I can even
do that, okay. So because I can think about
it purely from a mathematical perspective
so if my son is going to run till infinity
and the ? is less than 1 and remember that
each individually each r is bounded okay,
so this sum will converge to something finite
so I do not have to worry about what I had
in this case this sum will not explode okay,
so that is fine, right.
But there is even something more interesting
about this discounted reward formulation,
in fact originally when people propose a discounted
or what formulation it was not really from
the bounded ness point of view there is more
from a
from a psychology point of view immediate
gratification which is delay the gratification,
right so if you let us look at what happens
if ? is 0. All thing will go right, it is
just RT+1 this goes back to just optimizing
for the immediate payoff, right so this gives
you essentially you are going to behave in
a way so that the next time step what is the
maximum reward that you are going to get so
you are going to behave only in that way,
right.
So if you think about what ? is doing so it
is making suppose I get a 10 here which is
getting a 10 here so 10 here is more valuable
than 10 here right, of course 10 here is more
valuable than 10 here, right. So let us go
back to our robot grasping problem we are
talking about having a -1 all the time and
then giving you 100 when you actually grasp
so instead of that I can say I am going to
use the discounted rewards my ? say 0.8 so
what does it mean, so the sooner graspit the
larger the value I am going to see, correct.
So the overall reward I am starting from here
I should put myself in a trajectory so that
a graspit picks quickly. Otherwise I will
see some ?10,000x100 so that is very, very
small value so the shorter eyes I know I can
get rid of the -1 right. So I do not really
have to do the -1 but then what becomes tricky
here we have to figure out what is the right
value of gamma right, so that becomes tricky.
So this is, so they use this kind of ? to
control for whether you are a near sighted
agent will be worried about immediate gratification
or whether you are okay delaying the gratification
little bit so that you get a higher payoff
further down the line. The only 1, 1payoff
right, so just pull
what we do not cumulative or so you are talking
about regrets you are talking about regrets
right, we are talking about the total reward
case, right.
So yeah, having a discounter really does not
make sense, right so anyway you are trying
to optimize regret right, so in some case
your ? is as small as possible right when
you say you are optimizing regret that means
you are trying to keep your ? as small as
possible so essentially you want all your
winnings to come in one pool right and one
pull I want to be optimal, so that is your
optimal regret case, right.
So when you are trying to do achieve something
like this setting a ? does not make sense
right, but even if you can come up with a
different objective function maybe there is
something that you can think of or the entire
learning process, okay. So one thing which
I should point out just let me finish one
thing I should point out is that classically
the RL people right, look at bandit problems
as immediate RL right, I mean the learning
another the whole interaction is just that
one arm pull, okay that is how we think of
it while the, in the long-term case is the
full RL problem.
But if you look at the people who work in
the Bandit theory community right, they think
of the interaction as the entire learning
process, right that they do not think of it
as one arm pull they think of it as the whole
process itself is the learning process so
for them it is like an episode, right so there
is a very different mindset so the other people
do not think of it that way and the bandit
people do not think of discount factors and
other things because that is something which
the RL just came up with for looking at long-term
payoffs so there is a mismatch of vocabulary
there so maybe there is something to find
that in the middle ground but I am not sure.
Return is a function of the time step, yeah
here let us put it this way so I should optimize
my policy in such a way that wherever I am
starting from that and going forward I should
get maximum possible return. So even if I
am the last step I do not want to go from
the last step but if I am see, one thing you
should remember is that if I know where I
am going to end if that capital T is given
to me before hand then it becomes a non-stationary
problem.
Because I know okay, I have five more steps
to go what should I do I take one more set
I have only four more steps to go what should
I do so immediately the problem changes but
if I know the T then it is a non-stationary
sitting, right so we will not will not look
at cases where the T is known, okay we will
only look at cases where T is known to be
finite but not deterministic, right it is
not known if you are so it is not like I can
say that I will optimize only at the last
step or anything but I do not know what the
last step is, right.
I might recognize it when you actually reach
it but I do not know beforehand that okay,
I am going to have only so many substance
step to go, I mean this is the normal seeing
that we assume but you can immediately see
it is not realistic you know I mean when you
are playing chess you can always say I am
going to win in three more moves or well I
am going to lose in three moves it is depending
on right, so how well the game is going. So
in some cases you do have this kind of a little
bit of a forecasting ability as to what the
T is, but typical in the basic setup that
we will talk about will assume T is unknown.
The people understand why ?=1 closer to 1
is far sighted, right and closer to 0 is near
sighted okay. In the second equation R and
T bios to the action which is given as fast
as ever say I have five action possible and
I picked an action which is giving you everybody
in the first and there is another property
where I could pick another action first and
then this action later which is higher reward
in the longer run, so then in this equation
we are actually giving more reward to the
actually which is done.
Well, depends on many things right, depends
on the value of ? and depends on the magnitude
of the other rewards that you are getting
right, so let us say ? is 0.9999999. When
the bios is slow. When the bios is slow depending
on how far sighted you want to be you have
to pick your ?, right so they are unsatisfactory
you have another free parameter really free
parameter that you have no way how to tune
but yeah it is there and it is a well talk
about another reward formulation shortly.
Which gets results of the ? but makes it very
hard to optimize anyway so any other questions
on this. Yeah, sure, yeah but then that means
I am fall, I am failing after more time steps,
right so I am okay maybe that is positive
or negative it does not matter as far as this
return definitions are concerned, you are
essentially interested in maximizing the return
therefore if you are going to take an action
that gives you a -100 reward the farther out
in the future you take it is better, right.
So succeed for as long as you can and then
die you know right, so yeah it does not matter
so the rewards can be positive, negative.
So reinforcement learning is really the community
is little regret right, so we talk about positive
rewards and negative rewards then if you look
at the psychology literature they talk about
rewards and punishments right, for some reason
the RL community and if you look at the, you
know other places they call it payoffs right
or they call it cost negative rewards are
called costs but the RL community somehow
things of negative things also as rewarding
so we have positive rewards and you have negative
rewards but in the larger scheme of things
you know negative things also improve your
experience you know the enrich your life in
some way so you can think of negative rewards
also anyway.
So good so this is sign then we will move
on to one more definition how to give this
right, so what is that do just gives me the
average right, so the more the reward accumulate
the larger the average is going to be right
so for a finite number of n this makes sense
right, but what if I have an infinite number
of rewards in the future. Under mild regularity
assumptions and bounded-ness of the individual
Rs this will be bounded, okay.
What is not clear is that it will have actually
have a limit, might not right in general it
might not have a limit so you have to impose
additional constraints on the kind of problems
that you are solving not all problems have
this defined right or when you can make some
small variations to this to make sure that
all problems have this limit defined, okay.
So there are slight different the limit can
be we can play around with the limit.
For example one case where limit will not
exceed exists is this if the sequence is periodic,
right if the sequence is periodic then the
limit or not exist right, because it will
just keep oscillating all the time, right.
So in this case we use something called the
let me know how to handle limits of periodic
sequences use something called the cesaro’s
limit which essentially looks at the average
over periods and let us the number of periods
run to infinity, right so in the reason the
limit does not exist is because you cut the
sequence in the middle of a period where so
it is going to be periodic so you only take
a period as a unit and take the reward over
the period, right and then you keep adding
that over subsequent periods and take the
average, right and limit as the number of
such periods you consider it goes to infinity
is called the cesaro's limit.
Then in such cases limit might exist because
there are bunch of other condition you have
to put on the actual structure of the problem
itself for it ensure that this limit exists
but for a very broad class of problems you
can talk about this limits as well. So the
nice thing about this kind of the return definition
is that it does not have a pesky ? parameter
right so it makes it nice from a computational
point of view not to have the gamma parameter.
But it makes it little weaken from with the
one of the original motivations of RL point
of view because it does not have the ? parameter,
okay. So ? parameter allows you to have you
know some sense personality for your agent
that is it the near sighted agent or a far
sighted agent and so on so forth that so especially
people in neuroscience when they are looking
at modeling reinforcement learning humans
right, so they actually have they can think
of estimating what is your ? by running experiments
with you right.
Because it is kind of you know it is a personality
issue thing right, so some people will tend
to be in fact there are studies that try to
correlate the levels of serotonin in your
head to ?, right so more the serotonin the
larger the ? value you have in your decision
making and so on so forth I mean it is like
this is really weird how we seem to have all
these parameters in our head tied up with
the different kinds of neurotransmitters,
right anyway.
So this is called the average reward, this
is called average reward return so any case
is what this is called discounted return
that sorry I cannot hear, cumulative or total
return on right so people if you are going
to call that cumulating then you have to call
this cumulative discount, okay so there is
a very nice problem that people use for motivating
why discounted return is bad, okay. So let
me let me try and do that here, okay so I
am implying no theological leanings here okay
this is just a fun example, so that is earth
and it is heaven and that is hell so the path
to heaven has a -100 reward and the path to
hell has a +1000 reward right but once you
reach heaven you get a +1 infinitely once
you reach hell you get a -1 infinitely
I said I am not getting into theology here
okay, this is just a fun example of course
you can always think about other things here,
know you what for now anyway are finished
here right, this it is a transient state we
do not care.
But then if I said ? is 0.1 or something,
right you would prefer going to hell right
if ? is like 0.9 I said is ? has to be pretty
high for you to go to heaven right, so it
is the same problem so now ? becomes part
of the problem definition right, depending
on what value I set for ? my optimal policy
itself will change right, so there is not
a desirable state of affairs I mean if you
are thinking about saying okay here is a problem
solve it and it turns out that if I use average
reward scenario now which is better going
to heaven is better always does not on depend
on anything what does it depend on.
I mean if infinite number of +1s right that
will help any my negative things I get initially
I am getting a finite value for negative here
I am going to get a minus infinity there and
a plus infinity here so that trumps anything
that happens here, so average reward will
tell me that this is the best thing to do.
But if I am going to use discounted returns
so I will go up or down depending on what
my ? is right. So now you can immediately
see that discounted rate or is a more realistic
return because where everybody is going to
have it right anyway that is the fun part.
.
They come to the really one of the clerks
of a reinforcement learning here, right in
the full RL and a lot of the algorithm that
we look at and the notion of a value function.
But we already looked at the value function
right, but the value function we looked at
was very simplistic right so what did we do
that we said okay, average of all the words
I obtained so far right that is the value
function then we have another value which
he looked at which is the expected to expected
reward that I should get if I take an action,
right so we denote that by q* and then we
noted by q the average that I maintaining
for this right.
But here they are something more complex,
what do we have here we have a policy p which
determines not just the current reward but
also the sequence that I am going to see hence
forth right, so when I am going to talk about
a value function here I will talk about something
called Vp right, so Vp is the value function
associated with a policy p, right. So when
you say Vp(s) so this is essentially the expectation
of, so what should I be taking the expectation
of
rewards or returns what do you think it is
I should be taking the expectation of the
returns, right.
Because the return is what I am looking to
optimize this is what I should be predicting
so in the bandit case I was only looking at
the reward so I was just making out is the
expectation of the reward and here I should
make it out as the expectation of return so
given anything. Anything else, Oh quite I
need to condition it on p right, because I
already have a p here so why do I need to
condition on p because with Gt is going to
depend on p. Regardless of what formulation
I am using the subsequent rewards I am going
to get depend on the actions I take, right
so I nearly need to know what my p is right.
So I need to condition it on p so we will
denote it like this, right when I write the
p here that means that is a policy I am conditioning
off, okay the expectation with respect to
the distribution generated by following p
okay, of Gt given that at time Ti started
with state s okay, does it make sense everyone
on board, right so I am starting from state
s I am following pi am generating one trajectory
right like this right so I start from s okay,
go to some s' go to s'' so on so every time
I take an action so I will take a, a', a''
and so on and I will get some r, right this
is one trajectory.
So like that I will start from s, I will do
another trajectory then I will start from
s I will do another trajectory, I will start
from s I will do another trajectory then I
will be getting all these rewards like I have
r,r', r'' like that I will get some r1', r1''
and so on so for each trajectory I will get
one set sequence of rewards right, so I will
add up all of these or I will take a discounted
at sum of all of this right, so I will do
that right and I will take your average that
is that essentially whatever that average
will converge to is my expected value for
this is this is essentially what I mean.
When i say Gt says state t=s that means I
will start with s okay, and compute this rewards
okay, right. So is it clear why we need to
condition on the p as well write the future
is going to depend on p yeah, yeah they are
talking about the expectation here I just
explaining to you what the expectation is
so every time I generate the trajectory through
p right, two things could happen A I could
pick different actions because p is stochastic
B the world could change in a different way
because the world is stochastic, so the same
s I could take the same A I might end up in
a different desperate every time right, so
there are multiple ways in which the stochastic
can operate so one p itself is stochastic
therefore in the same s I need not take the
same action again.
Say first time I can take A1 next time I can
take A2 and so on so forth and that will completely
change the trajectory that will come later
or I will take the same A right, I might end
up in a different exponent because of the
transition probability so every time I do
this trajectory I will get some different
project development every time I generate
a trajectory I will get a different sequence
right, and the expectation is over all set
sequences you know what is the total reward
I will get so that is essentially what the
value functions, okay is it clear great.
.
Let us confuse people some more so we had
q earlier right so what was q(a)q*(a) was
the true think q(a) is the expectation we
are expected estimate for taking action A,
right but then here we have to worry about
taking action A in a specific state because
every state it is going to be different, correct
every state it will be different so what less
will be s will have to do this s still have
to do this, so what is a big difference between
the v and q sorry, yeah action A is fixed
so earlier when you are generating trajectories
for Vp I said you start with s right, then
you go to s' then you go to s'' and so on
so forth and then you could I said you could
pick any action.
So first time will pick a, a' so next time
you put some a1 so like this right, so you
could pick different actions every time we
generated the trajectory. So now I'm saying
you cannot do that right, so every time I
generate the trajectory you have to pick a
first right, but subsequently you pick actions
according to type the first action is something
that is fixed now the first action will be
a all the time so what does this tell you
it tells you how good is it to perform action
a in a given state. So earlier you did not
have that information but now you have the
information about how good is it to perform
actually in a given state, okay is
it clear going back and thinking about the
problem itself right. So there is a problem
that we are trying to solve right, so how
do you define the problem how do you characterize
the problem right, so I am in a state s I
take an action I go to a next state and I
also get a reward right.
So for me to characterize the problem I need
to tell you how this transitions happen and
how the reward generation happens right, so
I need to really look at this following question
what is a probability of given
is sorry.
.
RT+1 given this is sufficient I mean think
about it right, riding a bicycle so you probably
need to know what is the velocity momentum
that you had before and it is not enough to
know how you were on the road and how you
are tilting you might want to know something
more about the history of how you got there,
right. So you really need that quantity so
you need to know what is the probability of
s T+1 RT+1 given everything that went before
that, okay. Now this base is a little complex
to model because the number of parameters
you will need for modeling something like
this becomes pretty huge, right.
So what we typically end up doing is make
a very strong assumption that this guy is
equal to so what you truly need is the first
quantity right, because it becomes very hard
to estimate very hard to define you make the
assumption that that quantity is really equal
to this right so what is this assumption called
typically Markov assumption it is essentially
a first order Markov assumption where the
history does not matter right only the current
state and current action matters that will
determine what the next state and extraction
will be right.
So we make a further assumption which is where
s
is the assumption I made stationary, right
so we will typically operated it mark of environments
right and will typically assume their stationary,
okay. So for me to characterize a problem
now what should I give you
what I need is what is the question yeah,
to specify the problem what are the things
I should give you okay, I should give you
the states over which the problem is defined
right.
I need to do that right I need to define the
state space over which the problem is defined
and then the set of actions that I can take
and write the P function right, so I need
all of this to define the problem completely
anything else I need depends on what I see
return I am using I mean also need
a ? right. If my return if I am using a discounted
return depending on what the value of gamma
is the problem changes right that is what
we discussed.
So if I am going to use discounted return
I should also specify gamma as part of the
problem, okay this is clear so I need all
of this to define my problem right in some
cases we use a slightly simplified definition
where instead of having the single joint distribution
s/s' and r right, we also give it as two separate
quantities.
.
So I will suggest s I mean I have to specify
sa then I will specify that so what is that
call sometimes called the transition function
or transition probabilities okay, and then
I will specify
the expected value of the return given that
a Ti was in s I did action a underwent a s'
right, so essentially I am writing this out
splitting this up right, so instead of giving
the joint Distribution I am saying okay no,
no I will specify the s' separately and for
the R I will condition it on s' also right.
So I can we can think of some sense I am using
the chain rule and splitting that joint probability
as p(s') into P(r) given sa, sa' but what
is the difference here instead of specifying
p(r) given sa' I am giving you only the first
movement or zeroth moment in the first moment
of the distribution right, so why is this
enough because I am going to be optimizing
only the expected value of Gt, okay and then
Gt is composed of these guys right.
So essentially I will be taking the individual
expectations of each one of these right, and
that is enough for me, I do not really need
to know the distribution we generated these
rewards because individually I will be taking
the expectations of each one of these rewards
and therefore knowing the expectation alone
is enough so sometimes you specify the problem
like this right, and this is typically how
you would I would specify a what is called
a Markov decision process.
So it is a system is a decision system that
you have to for every state you have to actually
keep giving a decision right, and it follows
Markov in dynamics right, both the transition
and the rewards follow how when satisfy the
Markov property right, so such a system is
called a Markov decision process right so
we have states you have set of decisions right
and the evolution of the states follows the
Markov process okay so they are called Markov
decision process, okay and what we will assume
is that the reinforcement learning problems
that we are trying to solve can be modeled
as MDPs, okay.
We will assume that the reinforcement problems
you are trying to solve can be modeled as
MDPs so in some sense a value function really
you know is useful only if you have the Markov
property, why because I am assigning a value
to a state regardless of how I got to the
state right, so if the Markova property is
not satisfied how I got to the state will
influence what happens in the future right.
Since I am saying that no I do not care about
what happened in the past I am saying I am
starting in state s okay, I am going to be
following policy p here after what is the
expected return that for I am saying history
is irrelevant right, when I am defining a
value function another way of thinking about
it is here the value function is marginalizing
over history so it is essentially taking the
expectation regardless of what the history
was that is one way of looking at it I mean
in some cases that is how you make sense out
of the value functions.
Because as we go along later we will see that
we actually apply RL blind lead to problems
are non-Markov right and we will be using
the v function in the q function in such cases.
So the only way to make sense out of what
is happening in such cases is to say that
essentially marginalizing the history say
we are just doing the taking the expectation
over all possible industries as well and may
or may not be a sensible quantity.
But if it works you just use it right, but
normally you value function makes sense only
if you have the Markov property forget about
the future right, then the because you are
ignoring the past it makes sense only if you
have the Markov property right, it makes sense
right so that is why I was saying that I should
have probably defined value functions after
telling about Markova addition process but
it is okay, you can still understand it in
the general sense as well great. So the next
thing we have to talk about as optimal value
functions, right when I will start that in
the next class.